nevadahealthlink.com 2016-11-13

# Privacy Policy | Nevada Health Link

## Nevada Health Link Privacy Policy

Nevada Health Link will collect sensitive information from consumers in order to perform Nevada Health Link functions, such as enrollment in qualified health plans (QHPs) and eligibility for advance payments of the [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) tax credit ([APTC](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/)) and cost sharing reductions (CSR). Personally-identifiable consumer information (PII) and Protected Health Information (PHI) are protected by federal law and state laws. This Privacy Policy describes how information about covered persons or Nevada Health Link applicants may be used, disclosed, and accessed.

### What information will be collected?

Nevada Health Link will only collect the minimum information required to achieve its mission of providing affordable health insurance to individuals and small businesses in the State of Nevada. The information collected during the application process, enrollment, customer support, and renewals will only be used to ensure the efficient operation of the Nevada Health Link, verify the eligibility of an individual to enroll through Nevada Health Link or to claim a [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) tax credit or cost-sharing reduction, and the amount of the credit or reduction. This information will not be shared with any other person or entity unless it is required to determine eligibility or to enroll in a qualified health plan.

In order to facilitate enrollment in Nevada Health Link, and to determine eligibility for enrollment in qualified health plans (QHPs), advance payments of the [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) tax credit ([APTC](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/)), and cost sharing reductions (CSR), Nevada Health Link must collect information necessary to authenticate identity, citizenship status, residency, income, and incarceration status. This data includes, but is not limited to:

• **Demographic Data:** Name, Address, Phone Number, Email, Age

• **Income Data:** Tax Filing Status, Marriage Status, Tax Dependents, Employer, Annual or Monthly Income

• **Citizenship Data:** Social Security Number, Resident Alien Number, Native American Tribe ID Number, Incarceration Status

• **Disability Information:** Whether the applicant is blind, disabled, or requires assistance with daily living (this information cannot be used to deny coverage, but may help an individual to become eligible for Medicaid)

• **Payment Information:** Credit Card Numbers, Checking Account Numbers

• **Health Insurance Coverage Information:** Past and current health insurance coverage, tobacco use, consumer plan selections, and other information necessary to facilitate enrollment.

• **Pre-Authorizations, Current Episodic Status, Continuity of Care, etc.** : For individuals and families enrolling in Medicaid Managed Care Organization (MCO) Transition Qualified Health Plans who were formerly enrolled in a MCO Medicaid Plan, pre-authorized care and prescriptions, current treatment plans, and other continuity of care information will be transferred between the MCO Medicaid Plan and that MCO’s Transition Qualified Health Plan to ensure continuity of care for this special population.

This information is captured during the application and enrollment process and is used during annual open enrollments to provide an expedited enrollment experience.  To improve the Nevada Health Link portal and the overall usability of the site, some data regarding page views, browsing behavior, and system response times may also be collected. All personal data changes, eligibility results, plan selections, and any other action performed by the user will be tracked for audit and appeals purposes.

Each interaction between an individual and Nevada Health Link or the Customer Contact Center will also be documented along with any communications, notifications, or emails. The primary purpose of recording this information is to help improve the efficiency of the Customer Service Center, Nevada Health Link Operations, and to support the appeals process.

### What other parties will have access to my information?

Nevada Health Link will only share information with insurance carriers, and state and federal agencies as required to process requests for enrollment in QHP’s and to determine eligibility for health coverage, advance payments of the [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) tax credit, and cost sharing reductions. The following table outlines the entities Nevada Health Link will share data with, and how that data is used. All entities that receive data from Nevada Health Link are required to support the same level of data security standards as Nevada Health Link itself.

# | **E** **n** **t** **i** **ty** | **D** **ata** | **U** **sage of Data**  
---|---|---|---  
1. | Nevada Department of Welfare and Supportive Services (DWSS) | Individual Demographic, Income, Citizenship, Disability | The DWSS systems determine eligibility for public assistance, [APTC](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/), CSR, and for participation in Nevada Health Link itself.  
2. |  

Qualified Health

Plan Carriers

| Individual [APTC](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/) Amount, [Premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) Amount, Plan 

Selection, Payment Status, Enrollment Status

|  

The Carriers are notified of the customer’s plan selection, ongoing [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) payment status, and enrollment status.  
  
3. |  

Managed Care Organizations (MCOs)

| Pre-authorized care and prescriptions, 

current treatment

plans, and other continuity of care

information

| MCO’s will be notified when a member enrolls in a Medicaid MCO 

Transition Plan to allow the

Transition Plan access to the members’ former medical treatment

to coordinate continuity of care.  
  
4. |  

Nevada Division of Health Care Financing and Policy (DHCFP)

| Aggregated [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) disbursement and 

[premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) collection amounts

| As a division of the single state agency for Medicaid/CHIP, DHCFP 

is required to account for the state and federal funds disbursed through the program.  
  
5. | U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS) | Individual Enrollment, [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/), [APTC](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/) |  

Nevada Health Link is federally mandated to report enrollment, [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/), and [APTC](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/) amounts to CMS for each enrolled individual.  
  
**How do I know my information will be protected?**

Information collected by Nevada Health Link during the enrollment process is protected by several federal and state laws, including provisions in the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (PPACA), IRS Code, and Nevada regulations. In addition, Nevada Health Link has policies and procedures in place to ensure information security and privacy.  The following laws and guidelines are important safeguards in the protection of information shared with the Nevada Health Link:

45 CFR § 155.260 states that Nevada Health Link may only use PII to determine eligibility for enrollment in qualified health plans, to determine eligibility for Medicaid and the Children’s Health Insurance Program, and to determine eligibility for exemptions from the [individual mandate](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/individual-mandate/) to maintain health insurance coverage.  Nevada Health Link will fully comply with this federal regulation. Nevada Health Link will not create, collect, use or disclose personally identifiable information for any purposes that are not authorized under this regulation.1  The following principles are outlined in the regulation:

  * **Individual Access:** Individuals will be provided with a simple and timely means to access and obtain their personally identifiable health information

  * **C** **orrection:** Individuals will be provided with a timely means to dispute the accuracy of their personally identifiable health information and to have erroneous information corrected

  * **Op** **enness and transparency:** All policies, procedures, and technologies that affect individuals and their personally identifiable information are fully disclosed to the public

  * **Individual choice:** Individuals will be provided a reasonable opportunity and capability to make informed decisions about the collection, use, and disclosure of their personally identifiable health information

  * **C** **ollection, use, and disclosure limitations:** Personally identifiable health information will be created, collected, used, and/or disclosed only to the extent necessary to accomplish the goals of Nevada Health Link

  * **D** **at** **a quality and integrity:** Persons and entities will take reasonable steps to ensure that personally identifiable health information is complete, accurate, and up- to-date to the extent necessary to provide services to the members of Nevada Health Link

  * **S** **af** **eguards:** Personally identifiable health information is protected with reasonable operational, administrative, technical, and physical safeguards to ensure its confidentiality, integrity, and availability and to prevent unauthorized access, use, or disclosure

  * **Accountability:** These principles are implemented, and adherence assured, through independent security audits by a third party.

**Nevada Health Link will maintain operational, technical, administrative and physical safeguards**

Consistent with all applicable laws and regulations, Nevada Health Link will ensure that all information is protected through effective administrative and operational procedures maintained by Nevada Health Link.

  * Nevada Health Link will ensure the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of all personally identifiable information that is created, collected, used, or disclosed by Nevada Health Link.

  * Personally identifiable information will be used by, or disclosed to, only those authorized to receive or view it. PPACA section 1411 states that “an applicant for insurance coverage or for a [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) tax credit or cost-sharing reduction shall be required to provide only the information strictly necessary to authenticate identity, determine eligibility, and determine the amount of the credit or reduction.” It also states that this information must be used only for Nevada Health Link operations (such as verification of eligibility for enrollment, cost-sharing reduction, or [premium](https://www.nevadahealthlink.com/glossary/premium/) tax credit). Penalties of up to $25,000 per violation exist for anyone who knowingly and willfully violates this restriction.2

  * Tax return information will be kept confidential in accordance with section 6103 of the Internal Revenue Code. The IRS will disclose certain available items of federal tax return information to the Data Services Hub after an individual submits an application for financial assistance in obtaining health coverage with Nevada Health Link or state agencies that administer Medicaid, CHIP, or basic health plans. The items that will be disclosed through the Data Services Hub are described under Internal Revenue Code section 6103(l)(21)(A) and the regulations issued under that section. Internal Revenue Code section 6103 protects the confidentiality of federal tax return information.3  Disclosure of federal tax return information to the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services is allowed in order to implement eligibility determinations for health insurance affordability programs, within the confidentiality requirements in Internal Revenue Code section 6103.4

  * Personally identifiable information will be protected against any reasonably anticipated threats or hazards to the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of such information.

  * Personally identifiable information will be protected against any reasonably anticipated uses or disclosures that are not permitted or required by law.

  * Personally identifiable information will be securely destroyed or disposed of in an appropriate and reasonable manner and in accordance with retention schedules.

**Nevada Health Link will maintain appropriate security controls**

  * Nevada Health Link will ensure that its workforce complies with all information safeguards and security controls.
  * Nevada Health Link will monitor, periodically assess, and update security controls to ensure the continued effectiveness of those controls.
  * Nevada Health Link will require, as a condition of contracts and agreements, the same or more stringent privacy and security standards and controls to Navigators, agents, brokers or other contractors authorized to access any personally identifiable information.
  * Nevada Health Link will use secure electronic interfaces when sharing personally identifiable information electronically. PPACA section 1413 requires the establishment of secure electronic interfaces with state health subsidy programs allowing the Nevada Health Link to be consistent with privacy and security standards in section 1942 of the Social Security Act. Nevada Health Link will ensure that all data matching and data sharing arrangements between Nevada Health Link and agencies administering the Medicaid and Children’s Health Insurance Program meet all requirements applicable to Nevada Health Link as well as all requirements applicable under Medicaid and the Children’s Health Insurance Program.

**Nevada Health Link Will Comply With Nevada Privacy and Information Security  ** **P** **olicies and Standards**

Nevada Health Link follows standards, policies, and procedures designed to protect personal health information (PHI), personally identifiable information (PII), financial information and plan information entrusted to Nevada Health Link. Nevada Health Link’s portal and supporting systems adhere to federal security mandates and standards, in particular:

  * Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) Security and Privacy Rules

  * National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) guidelines, industry practices for security, confidentiality and auditing

  * Nevada State-specific security requirements to secure data and information, including but not limited to NRS, 205.4742 and chapter 603A.

  * Nevada Health Link systems and operations comply fully with the Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard (PCI DSS).

**What should a consumer do if they believe their Personal Information was unintentionally disclosed?**

If a consumer believes their Person Information was disclosed to an unintended outside source, or that it may have been accessed without the Exchange's knowledge they should contact the Exchange Consumer Assistance Center (ECAC) as quickly as possible in order to investigate that matter. The ECAC can be reached by calling 1-855-7NVLINK (855-768-5465), or TTY 1-855-853-8100 for those who are deaf, hearing or speech disabled.
